#### M. Susan Schmidt, PhD

(252) 269-0032; susu@starfishnet.com; www.susanschmidt.net

#### **Developmental and Technical Editor**

### **Qualifications Summary**

Dr. Schmidt is an Author, Editor, and Educator with 30 years experience as college and secondary teacher of creative and technical writing, literature, science policy, planning, and ethics; and 20 years as government editor and science analyst. Worldwide she edits books and locally she leads Beaufort Writing Group. Half retired, she calls contra dances, coaches rowing and sailing, swims, practices yoga, walks dogs, builds community gardens. She just renewed her US Coast Guard Captain's license the seventh time (35 years). As naturalist and Quaker, Susan walks to witness natural diversity: recently the Camino de Santiago and the Cornwall Coastal Path. Winner of 2012 Guy Owen Poetry Prize. Published poem in *Literary Trails of Eastern North Carolina*.

#### **Work History**

# Developmental Editor, Beaufort Writing Group, Beaufort, NC January 2009 to Present

Advise authors on narrative structure; copyedit grammar and style. Edited *The Beach Book, Science of the Shore* (Columbia University Press, 2012) by Carl H. Hobbs, nominated for PROSE award. Quarterly copyeditor: Harvard Business School's *Business History Review* (Cambridge University Press). Edited 8 novels, including *Song of the Mokihana*, T. D. Matzenik, 1917 Pacific schooner novel; *Light on Water*, C. L. Rawlins, a New Zealand Maori saga; 10 memoirs. Editor of scientific documents, dissertation proofreader for non-native English speakers. Leader: Writing Critique Group & beginning and advanced workshops. Lecturer: NC Humanities on ecological history/ coastal issues. Moderator: 2011 NC Literary Homecoming, East Carolina University.

# **University Professor and Secondary Teacher**

1973 to 2009

Taught university technical and creative writing, American literature, creative nonfiction, environmental literature & philosophy, science communication, conflict resolution, environmental policy & community planning, science & religion at Carteret Community College 2001-2008 & 1979-83, Hampton University 2007, Brevard College 1996-2001, Warren Wilson College 1994-95, NC School of Science & Math 1989-94, Duke University 1989-93, College of Charleston 1987-88, NC State University 1983, University of Virginia Engineering School 1979. Taught secondary literature, journalism, French, global environmental issues at SC Governor's School in Charleston 1988, Philips Academy in Andover, MA 1989 & 1969, Collegiate School in Richmond, VA 1973-76. Fellow at NEH Environmental Imagination Institute at Vassar, National Humanities Center, NC Center for Advancement of Teaching, Duke University Environment, Natural Resources Leadership.

### **Curriculum Designer, Grant-Writer, Fellowships**

1976 to 2010

Wrote research grants and land-acquisition (for Nature Conservancy) topping \$5 million. Designed interdisciplinary curriculum for NC State University on humanities for engineering students, Duke University on environmental philosophy for adults and 9<sup>th</sup>-graders, Medical University of South Carolina on AIDS Education and on Medical Ethics for Family Doctors, Stratford Hall on environmental history, Christchurch School on interdisciplinary environmental experiential Chesapeake studies, Brevard College and NC School of Science & Math on environmental humanities. Received scholarly grants from American Association of University Women on Southern Appalachian native plants & traditional music, National Endowment for the Humanities to design interdisciplinary environmental-humanities curriculum, National Science Foundation on interbasin water-transfer, Environmental Protection Agency on nonpoint-source-pollution runoff control, Office of Education for land-use/ water-quality workshops, Fulbright Foundation to teach English in West Germany. Creative-writing fellowships: VA Center for Creative Arts in VA 2000 and SW France 2008, Vermont Studio Center for fiction workshop 2006, Environmental Writing Workshop/ Montana 2000, Bread Loaf for nonfiction workshop 1999, Hambidge Center/ Georgia 1999; NC Arts Council to research Captain John Smith and Jamestown 2002.

# Contract Technical Editor & Workshop Trainer 1996 to 2008 USDA Forest Service, Southern Research Station, Asheville, NC, and Atlanta, GA

Edited scientists' journal articles and books, including *Southern Appalachian Assessment*; Deerskins And Cotton, Ecological... Savannah River before 1950; *Ecology, Fifty Years on Savannah River Site*. Led workshops (in grammar, style, logic, & law) training endangered-species biologists to write legally-defensible environmental-assessment documents. Led grant-writing workshops for scientists; edited silviculture symposia proceedings.

#### Environmental Scientist/ Policy Analyst/ Editor/ Mediator 1977 to 2001

For NC Natural Resources Leadership Institute mediated between NC Forest Resources & Natural Heritage to protect natural areas and wrote recreational-management plan for 12,000-acre DuPont State Forest. Mediated for Transylvania Dispute Settlement Center, Brevard, NC. Edited Environmental Science Dictionary, Bruccoli Clark. As Virginia Sea Grant Editor, VIMS, College of William & Mary, edited two monthly newsletters on commercial fishing and marine-science research. Edited *San Diego Log* (waterfront newspaper). As Environmental Scientist for NC Coastal Management, Morehead City, wrote policy reports and testified to Coastal Resources Commission on land use regulations to protect estuarine water quality, including wetland mitigation, coal ports, oil refineries; wrote grant proposal and management plan to establish NC Estuarine Research Reserve. For Nature Conservancy as steward, wrote Carrot Island Preserve Management Plan, Beaufort, NC; wrote acquisition grant and management plan for Ivy Creek Natural Area, Charlottesville, VA. For US Department of Interior, Washington, reviewed environmental-impact statements on dams, mediated among departments to write Secretary's letter.

#### Education

Conflict-Resolution Fellow, Natural Resources Leadership Institute, NC State University, 1998-2000 Bioethics, Environmental Philosophy Fellow, Duke University Divinity School, 1990-93 PhD, American Literature, University of South Carolina, 1990

MA, Environmental Sciences, University of Virginia, 1980 Watershed ecology, water quality
 Botany study, Highlands (UNC), 1996, Mt. Lake (UVa) biology stations, 1976, 1990
 MA, English, University of Virginia, 1972; Teaching License in English, Science, French, Reading (7-12<sup>th</sup> grades)
 BA, English; French, German Connecticut College, May 1971; Oxford University, England, Honors 1969-70

#### **Publications**

Dr. Schmidt is author of *Landfall Along the Chesapeake, in the Wake of Captain John Smith* (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2006), gave 100 lectures on Chesapeake ecological history. She published 10 poems (*Southern Poetry Review, Literary Trails of Eastern North Carolina, Kakalak, ISLE, Tar River Review, Land Report*), 5 book chapters, 7 literary essays (*Shenandoah, Milkweed* anthology), 10 journal articles, 150 magazine/ newspaper articles. She edited 25 technical books, science reports & proceedings, 18 novels & memoirs.

# **Selected Honors & Fellowships**

2012 Guy Owen Poetry Prize, Poem in *Literary Trails of Eastern North Carolina* (UNC Press, 2013) VA Center for Creative Arts Fellowship SW France & VA; NC Arts Council grant Vermont Studio Center, Bread Loaf, Robert Ruark Fiction Award, NC Writers Blumenthal Reader Montana's Environmental Writing Program; Orion's Fire & Grit, Ossabaw Southern Nature Writers National Endowment for Humanities 2 Fellowships, AAUW, NSF, Fulbright Most Influential Teacher of 2 highest graduates of NC State University; 12 Brevard College graduates

**Member**: Editorial Freelancers Association, Science Writers, Association for Study of Literature & Environment, National Association of Science Writers, American Association of University Women Association of Writing Programs, Poets & Writers, NC Environmental Educators

**Recent Travel:** Cornwall Coastal Path May 2012, Kenya Bird Survey Winter 2011. Walked Camino de Santiago Pilgrimage Path in Spain and France 2007 & 2008. Trekked in New Zealand Winters 2008 & 2010, Ireland 2006. Kayaked 500 miles NC/SC 1999, Alaska 1983. Delivered sailboats to West Indies 1980s

**Volunteer:** NC Maritime Museum Junior Sailing Program; Wounded Warriors Rowing Coach, Camp Lejeune; Carteret Local Food Network, Town of Beaufort Strategic Planning Committee